[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, there's always this gap between self and others, other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's never... it can never be filled.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you know, you can never get to anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: That self can never own anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's always this abyss that can never be crossed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that gap is the result of you assuming the sense of self, which obviously automatically means assuming the self of others, or rather
[SPEAKER_01]: Assuming self internally, assuming self externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for as long as that assumption is given the priority, as long as it's the center of your acts and thinking, there will be a gap generated as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is a mistake, so to speak, but it's a beginningless mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, the gap is real, and the sense of self is real, and the sense of others is also real.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just have to reverse it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of me trying to fill this gap, trying to possess this gap, trying to acquire things and others, or whatever else, you realize
[SPEAKER_01]: that the whole picture is upside down.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's actually you are the result.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your sense of self, sense of others, is the result of the gap that's impossible to own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not me reaching out to
[SPEAKER_01]: Possess the gap, to fill the gap.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically gap defining me as... as... as... well, as that being that's in lack, that's lacking, that's in the need, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you recognize that actually you are secondary, your sense of self is secondary to the gap, and you start seeing gap as a phenomenon, then you... well, you start reaching for it less and less, because you recognize actually reaching is the result of the gap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not that reaching is the beginning, where you kind of try to get the gap and fill it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there's a... You feel the need to fill because the gap is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you appropriate the gap, you appropriate the need to fill.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or if you appropriate the possibility of that gap being filled through your assumption, you will then crave to fill the gap.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that would be possible if the gap hasn't arisen there beforehand, on its own, manifested, arisen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you recognize that this need to fill it, it's because it has arisen as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not you filling it, or trying... you trying to fill.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or that it needs to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The gap arises as a gap.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then the need to fill doesn't belong to anybody, and then you stop filling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it is need for oneness, or the idea that oneness... That's only the result of the separation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like unity implies separation.
[SPEAKER_01]: As much as separation implies the possibility of unity, but abandoning both means none of it is applicable anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people would think they have unity, but it's only because they maintain the idea of separation through craving for unity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you have to abandon both.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to see that whether it's separating or united, or both separate or united, neither separate nor united, it's irrelevant and it's determined by the presence of the gap beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence of the senses beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't stop that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't stop that.
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say beforehand, I mean structurally before, not temporarily before.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, things arise on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: They manifest, including your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, obviously, you appropriate them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You assume that the ownership, in hindsight, in retrospect, that was mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that things arise on their own means you're not their creator.
[SPEAKER_01]: They arise to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might feel that they're arising for you, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But all of that is secondary to their arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's seen like that, then the whole idea of unity, separation, filling the gap, craving for it, impossible, insatiable, you can't satisfy desires or whatever else, all that is the result of the things that have already arisen and you appropriate them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you appropriate them, means you fall under... well, you become a victim, so to speak, of their inherent pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the pressure of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Senses are like wild animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: They want to go and feed where they want to go and feed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You take them to be yours, means you are going there to feed.
[SPEAKER_01]: They are dragging you left and right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a crocodile, a monkey, wild boar, all those similes are for the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: But they do that on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's their business.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just you are interfering with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are trying to own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, because they're stronger than you, they'll take you with you.
[SPEAKER_01]: With them, sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're stronger than them, then you'll be in control of the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the only way to be stronger than your senses is to let go of them, to recognize for what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, that is possible to do only once you have restrained them.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sīla comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the whole idea of filling that gap, which just becomes inconceivable, because that gap was only the result of maintaining that mistake of ownership, that then, in return, would be feeding more of the desire for ownership, because it's obvious that you can't own, but you took the whole... like... you took it... the entire situation is taken in an upside-down manner, and that's... and that is taken for granted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter how much you kind of... your experience shows you that you can't fill that gap, that you can't own things, you never really question that assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just keep doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just keep each time and you can't help it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even you say, yeah, my desires cannot be satisfied, but you can't help going after them, because the five senses are pulling you and you're too weak.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to start realizing, hold on, what if I've taken this completely the wrong way around?
[SPEAKER_01]: What if it's not supposed to be filled?
[SPEAKER_01]: And what if that whole idea of filling this gap and these desires is the result of me trying to fill the gap and the desires?
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you constantly trying will make you want to try.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a vicious circle.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just goes around.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the entire thing is entirely gratuitous.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just there's nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there could be a desire
[SPEAKER_00]: If you look at marriage and relationships like that, the desire to be united with the other person, the love, this constant craving... Yeah, there's no problem with craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: The purest of the world, well, any form of love, for that matter, actually, it's just absolutely rooted in attachment, rooted in craving, rooted in that assumption of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, there is pure love, and pure love is pretty much craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because once that's in play, that love, that desire to... for oneness, there's suffering constantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for as long as you take that assumption for granted, means you will keep trying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you never... you will never take all of the signs of your experience that are showing you that you can't actually fill that gap, nor can you satisfy your desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will never take that as a... as a sign, as an indication that actually, hold on, maybe it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you do, you don't take it on a deeper level, whereby it will make you stop going after it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, people can, on a shallow level, on a shallow mental level, they can realize, oh yes, sure, yeah, of course, I mean, the life is pointless and you can't really satisfy your desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that won't sink in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they don't make enough effort for it to sink in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And why?
[SPEAKER_01]: More importantly, because they don't
[SPEAKER_01]: Develop their behavior beforehand, as in practice virtue, restraint and sīla, then it will sink in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it can't sink in, because their behavior contradicts it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The behavior goes against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no matter how much mentally you might be reflecting about how the unsatisfying pursuit of desire is there, if your acts are still aimed at the pursuit of desire, it means, like, whatever you're thinking won't bear much significance, because there's nowhere to land.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your actions are just swiping it all away, just poof, immediately, because they're still going full power after desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you actually have to stop that first, endure that initial pain, and then these reflections will be able to sink in and land on the proper ground that you created through restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the important thing to remember.
[SPEAKER_01]: The craving, the desire to fill the gap, is basically the result of the desire to fill the gap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because something can lack something else, only in regard to a different thing, if you know what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a gap is to be filled only in regard to a filled gap.
[SPEAKER_01]: In itself, an empty hole, a gap, it's a thing in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's no desire to be filled.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you project the assumption of a full hole, filled hole, leveled hole, completed hole, then this will seem incomplete.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the... and because you appropriate it, then you feel the pressure of that incompleteness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You too... because you... you stick your hand in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wasn't yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just wanted... you just don't know how to not make it yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then you just become a victim of that pressure of fill it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fill that gap.
[SPEAKER_01]: Satisfy those desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in itself, as I said, like we spoke before, an itch, physical itch that you want to scratch, in itself, it's just an itch.
[SPEAKER_01]: In comparison to the state that it's free of itch, oh, you feel pressure of scratching it, because scratching it might make it stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: The itch might bring it to an end, which is more pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, you follow more pleasure, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, so, having a non-desire, having a satisfied desire, it's more pleasant than having a desire that is not satisfied, that is more unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will always pursue the satisfaction of desire, no matter how futile it is, no matter how much you know that it's futile, you will pursue it for as long as you hold the assumption of the pleasure that you get through desires.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means you always go after it, because it's based on emotional level.
[SPEAKER_01]: You pursue pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, filling a gap, you keep doing it, because you assume that doing it is more pleasant than not doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you fail to see that through doing it, you maintain that discrepancy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you keep projecting the discrepancy that's created by you wanting
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasurable experience of a filled gap, as opposed to a gap that's not filled.
[SPEAKER_01]: A hole, that it's hollow, that it's empty.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you stop holding on to the assumption of a filled gap, then the discrepancy won't be hurting you anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, there is no more pressure of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because an empty hole, it's a thing in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: A full hole, it's a thing in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: A perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why, that's why, that's why, like in the in the simile of scratching the edge
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, you maintain the itch through constantly scratching it, because through scratching it, you prevent it from healing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You keep maintaining that discrepancy through your acts of scratching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, it will keep itching.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I meant before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through pursuit of desire, you maintain desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's as simple as that.
[SPEAKER_00]: In terms of, like, perceptions, in pursuit of perceptions... Yeah, you perceive those, those... Getting involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those... that perception of a filled hole,
[SPEAKER_01]: of a complete desire, it's inciting, it's pleasant, as opposed to the incomplete.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because you crave for pleasure, you go after that perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop craving for pleasure, then, yeah, there is a more agreeable perception, there is a more disagreeable perception, but none of them
[SPEAKER_01]: Need to be appropriated because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And none of them will be appropriated if you sort of relinquish the idea of that sensual pleasure that you get through pursuit of such perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it was said it's impossible to engage in sensuality without sensual perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because some people were claiming, saying, oh, you can, you know, you can be free from sensuality and still engage, I don't know, in an intercourse or various things, because there were loads of Brahmins and ascetics sort of claiming the ultimate nibbāna, yet, you know, having wives and whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would say it's impossible, it's inconceivable to be able to engage in sensuality, in an act of sensuality, without having those sensual perceptions established before it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as I said, the sensual perceptions are the distortion
[SPEAKER_01]: Did you assume, as such, as real?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's all you have at the top.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a... there's a... an edga sappaya sutta, 106, majjhima, in regard to the base of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's three ways to attain the base of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it says... it goes on...
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, Bhikkhu is a noble disciple, considers thus essential pleasures here and now, and essential pleasures in life in life to come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Essential pleasures here and now, and essential pleasures in life to come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, essential perceptions here and now, essential perceptions in life to come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Material forms here and now, material forms in life to come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perception of forms here and now, perceptions of forms in life to come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perceptions of the imperturbable and air-generated.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The rest is a kind of strange translation.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the dissolution of the body after death, it is possible that the evolving consciousness... That's another dodgy translation.
[SPEAKER_00]: ...may pass on to rebirth in the base of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the first way directed to the base of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The first way that you can attain this base of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, where is this... where these perceptions cease without remainder, that is peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the base of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you... where is that base of nothingness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the perceptions are absent.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, well, first thing I would point out, with regard to this, is that when it comes to base of nothingness and similar descriptions, people immediately assume, and that is thanks to the commentaries in contemporary Buddhism, people assume it's a meditative attainment, it's some sort of
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a blanked-out, spaced-out state.
[SPEAKER_01]: But as you can have just a little perspective, it's quite clear that it's nothing to do with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, he said, it is also from wisdom upon that state.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you actually understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not a meditative attainment in a conventional sense of that word.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can call that meditation, but that would be the right meditation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, another thing I would point out, the paragraph starts with the Noble Disciple.
[SPEAKER_01]: The right view has to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if the right view is there, even such, again, inverted commas, meditative attainments are actually devoid of the right view and wisdom, because that's what meditation is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cultivation of the right view that you already have beforehand.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this particular instance, in terms of the... well, you can... you don't have to go as far as the empathetic perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, you recognize the nature of perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's where it starts.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the central, the coarsest, central perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here, in the future lives, then there are the form, the perceptions of form.
[SPEAKER_01]: Here, in the future lives, then even the most peaceful perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the imperturbable, regardless of the diversity of the form, the perceptions of the imperturbable means basically what you discern through the nature of perception, because that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What's in common to essential perceptions, to perceptions of form, to the imperturbable perceptions?
[SPEAKER_01]: As it says, they're all perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: They all share the nature of perception, sañña, as an aggregate, and which means that discernment can be established on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't care what perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't care if it's diversified or unified.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't care if it's imperturbable or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is established upon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, through the discernment of the nature of perception, you can see, okay, it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that sublime, refined, imperturbable nature of perception, regardless of the particular manifestations of that perception, that perception has arisen.
[SPEAKER_01]: As such, it ceases, without a reminder, when the time comes, and there is nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nothingness can... it's sort of perceived in an indirect manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't perceive nothingness directly, but you can certainly establish your mind in regard to it, in an indirect manner, by surmounting the sphere of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's done through understanding, through, like, through real, correct phenomenology, knowledge of phenomena, knowledge of arisen things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not through, like, you know, watching the nostrils and then entering the astral projection of I don't know what.
[SPEAKER_00]: He resolves upon wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You said, or he resolves upon... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But either he wants... wants to his full confidence...
[SPEAKER_01]: Either his full confidence establishes his mind, right there and then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means he's living it and knowing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or he fully discerns it and resolves upon wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he... he also knows it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's read the other two ways, because it might be wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, because a noble disciple goes on to the forest, or to the root of a tree, or to an empty lot, considers thus, this is void of a self, or of what belongs to a self.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he's practicing this way, and frequently abides thus, his mind acquires confidence in this place, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Void off.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, as I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience, the inner experience, gives priority to the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with the right view, and yeah, you go to physically, to an empty room, that it's empty, it's factually empty, and you use that reflection as factual emptiness of this room.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same mirroring situation of the emptiness of the sense of self in this experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, it's a negative presence.
[SPEAKER_01]: This room is empty of others.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, others are present as absences in this room.
[SPEAKER_01]: Others are absent here.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is this body, so is this mind, and so on, absent of this self?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the self is only a negative phenomenon in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you start seeing it as such, you stop regarding it as yours, and you certainly stop regarding it as a center of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're seeing things like the body...
[SPEAKER_00]: Empty of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not empty of body, it's empty...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's empty of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's got a room there, it's got a body, it's feelings there...
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's empty of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that doesn't mean that this doesn't exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, if you say, oh, this room is empty of self... No, self exists as an absence, as a thing that's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's enough for you to stop regarding it as yours and that's all that matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that phenomenon that you've taken to be yourself, it's there, it's just not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a different way of saying that this experience here is empty of this my-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the self is absent and through that absence I can't own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, that absence is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: The absence of self is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you won't be able to designate it or talk about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by recognizing it, that it's absent, means, well, it can't be yours, because if it's yours, you'll have it all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is an empty sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's enough for you to stop regarding it as belonging to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, he attains the base of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, he attains the base of voidness, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Once there's full confidence, he either takes it to the base of nothingness now, or else he resolves upon it with wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through the perception of avoidance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, he stops appropriating any perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: This room is empty of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, through not being able to appropriate your sense of self, there's nothing that belongs to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You resolve upon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means nothing that arises, nothing that manifests, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: none of the perceptions that arise, no matter how sublime or diversified,
[SPEAKER_01]: It can be appropriated either.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pretty much nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't see nothingness in a direct manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only by surmounting perception, mind can get established upon nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, I always want to... And you can surmount the perception by resolving upon wisdom of, like, over the sphere of perception, outside of the perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, again, it's still, even the resolving upon wisdom, it's still done, like you, you establish yourself upon nothingness in that negative manner, through wisely surmounting the sphere of perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it all revolves around appropriation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the first example you gave of sensuality and different perceptions and so on, imperturbable, or the voidness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, voidness.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, in our case, nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was always...
[SPEAKER_00]: I wanted to imagine nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Imagination
[SPEAKER_01]: If your mind is developed in regard to your, or let's say more correctly, abstraction, some imagination, because it's kind of based on the facts, but you're not really living those facts, thus you're just abstracting the thinking, abstract, abstract thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't correspond.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if your mind was to be established upon that abstract thinking, it would cease to be abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will become, oh, a valid thought that has served to establish your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like what we spoke before, you use more general perceptions to abandon more particular, more diversified, more troublesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Upon the perceptions of the forest, you abandon perceptions of the village, which means whatever disturbance arises on account of perceptions of the village, cannot affect you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the... any disturbance that arises on account of perceptions of the forest, that can still affect you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you recognize that, so you go even higher.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is even greater perception than perception of forest and perception of earth?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, in this case, you can go even higher than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say, well, what is the perception?
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception of village, perception of forest, perception of earth, they're all perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And perception is... and a reasoned thing has to cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, whatever is perceived, whatever arises, has to come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is...
[SPEAKER_01]: Resulting upon that, it's the experience of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: The perception of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can then start discerning the perception of that nothing, so to speak, in regard to the positive perception that you have surmounted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because obviously there's a surmounting of that perception as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is higher than base of nothingness as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a third way to take nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, because the Noble Disciples considers thus, I'm...
[SPEAKER_00]: I am not anything belonging to anyone, anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, what did I say just before?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all about appropriation of belonging.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nor is there anything belonging to me in anyone, anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he practices in this way, it frequently binds us.
[SPEAKER_00]: His mind acquires confidence in this base.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once there's full confidence, he attains to the base of nothingness or results.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the most refined way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it really points out the appropriation, the belonging, taking his mind, which is what all I've been talking about so far.
[SPEAKER_01]: The first one is just sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: What was the other one?
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensual perceptions?
[SPEAKER_01]: Perceptions of form and then perceptions of imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that already implies me and mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the second one, it's a bit more personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's, oh, these perceptions here, this room, as this room is void of others, so this is void.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the third one, it's even more pointed out to just that experience of mind, not even necessarily the fully-blown sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: But either way, whichever you take, if you develop it, it will lead you to that samādhi, to the point of perception of nothingness, being established upon perception of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, by having nothing, like nothing here belongs to me, or do I belong to anyone?
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing in the future will belong to me, or will I belong to...
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing in the past has belonged to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... That's not possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not possible for anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not that it didn't belong to me, but it could.
[SPEAKER_01]: When he says nothing in the future, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means a present possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, nothing in the future will belong to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible for things to belong to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: And by truly permeating your whole experience with that recognition, that ownership is inherently impossible,
[SPEAKER_01]: You surmount the entire sphere of ownership, which is a sphere of perceptions, sphere of things that you can perceive, including abstract, remote, ambiguous thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: They appear as such, you can entertain the idea of ownership as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But fully cultivating this attitude, eventually it will permeate and saturate your experience entirely, in all of its sort of proliferated branches, so to speak, and that ownership will fade.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just because you recognize... you recognize that the only reason you were entertaining notions of ownership, it was by not fully, not emotionally understanding that you were not able to own them in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you were owning them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were appropriating them because you didn't know that you actually can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Appropriation is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the stopping of their pursuits is... Well, it's a result of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, like, there won't be... well, then pursuit will become equally inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the entire nature of pursuit was based upon that misperception.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it goes on to say that the... the base of neither perception or non-perception is the highest.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said,
[SPEAKER_01]: Negative... like what I gave the example before.
[SPEAKER_01]: The perceptions of forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you're in the village, your mind gets established upon perceptions of the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you enter the village, that perception, the forest, becomes a negative perception in regard to your current perceptions of the village.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because your mind is still established upon that perception, which is being perceived in a negative manner, nothing bothers you in the village that you can perceive, that you perceive, that you might perceive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you recognize, okay, so I live in the forest, when I'm in the village, if I'm established upon the perception of the forest, I'll be free from disturbance in the village, but not from the disturbance in the forest.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the negative perception in regard to the forest and the village, further down, it's the perception of earth, the entire earth, the element of earth.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a negative perception in regard to this more particular perception, or you can say more general perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a negative when you're perceiving other things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's present as an absent perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's ultimately nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shares that very nature of that very principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Quiet, Timmy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oops, sorry.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, through cultivating the negative perceptions...
[SPEAKER_01]: Your mind gets resolved upon it and establishes in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that is a perception in that negative manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: In that indirect manner, it's still our perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, neither perception nor no perception would be a state that goes even beyond that perception of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of the absence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, just general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, so as this village is absent of any forest and perceptions of forest, so is this entire body.
[SPEAKER_01]: that I'm now using on this particular level, walking through a village, is also absent of any owner, of any self that actually owns it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, more specifically, more precisely, as the third example says, of any belonging to the sense of self, or whatever arises in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, the sense of self, or rather, that which is taken to be a sense of self, stays there, but it loses its ownership, loses its belonging.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's not really a self anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can submerge neither perception nor perception through the entire cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, OK. Because, as I said, when that big... when that big hook clings,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because if you assume, if your upādāna is based upon neither perception nor perception, meaning the mind has been developed to such an extent that it can actually discern that state, which means all of the more diversified states have been abandoned and you cannot entertain any notions of ownership in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, when you learn and you get established upon the perceptions of forests and wilderness, the idea of a village, of a crowded place, the mind just will not go there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But imagine if you establish it to such a refined point, a refinement, whereby you surmount the perception in its entirety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that is the sublime.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, you can assume that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be kind of entertaining certain assumptions in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that means that all the other assumptions, all of it, not just the coarse ones, even the ones that are regarded relatively non-coarse, have been abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that is the place.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you want to create something, develop your mind and cling to that freely, because actually there isn't much there to cling on to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, as a result of that, you abandon all the other more dangerous assumptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Guru says when someone's practicing for nibbāna...
[SPEAKER_01]: They need to abandon that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Here, because practicing thus, it might not be and it might not be for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will not be and it will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: What exists, what has come to be, that's... That's basically...
[SPEAKER_00]: Abandoning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is developing that reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're not just... because as we said before...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, he's saying...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just the fact that you can't know now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fail is to recognize that even a possibility of ownership cannot occur.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you might think, okay, I don't know anything now, but you can still entertain implicitly, or rather tacitly assume within that ambiguous...
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply assume by not looking at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You end up assuming that tiny little remote possibility of ownership still might be possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you will entertain that by default, simply by not not entertaining it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not looking at that possibility as impossible, you will automatically entertain the notion of that possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the reflection, it might not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it will not even be possible for it to be for me, let alone be for me now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you really pervade, so to speak,
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole sphere of nature of possibility, which is much subtler than anything that isn't present in front of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I have this present instinct, I don't own anything, but you still entertain the possibility of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you never give in to it, you might entertain it for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you want to practice for nibbāna, an ultimate relinquishment, you start really targeting, so to speak, those possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, okay, it's obvious I don't own anything in front of me, around me, anything in the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, I couldn't have kept it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can still cherish a tiny little notion of... just the possibility of ownership as an abstract idea, even that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that will be the point that you're touching, the point that you're interfering with, the point that you didn't let go of.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you practice, it will not be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It cannot be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just... it's impossible for it to be for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter what, when, in the future, how far, how long in the future, it's just... it's impossible for this domain, the touch, to come together and establish belonging.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you practice that long enough, presently, right here, right now, in regard to the future possibilities, and, yeah, that is nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess we have, again, this moment of the gap, impossibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as you can see, that gap can obviously stretch to very refined levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you can, you can surmount, and even Pratyusha can surmount the gap of sensual craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the gap of the future ownership, like the possibility of ownership, can still be very much maintained.
[SPEAKER_01]: But by recognizing that that gap is insurmountable, that it's impossible to fill, impossible to bridge, you stop trying to build a bridge.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will keep trying to build a bridge for as long as you think it's possible for it to work, it's possible to build it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You remove it, or rather you remove the hope, the notion of that possibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: You fully understand it as, oh no, this is impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, all of the efforts to build a bridge just... you don't have to then go... you automatically... they stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: They disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all... the key thing is all the suffering ends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the result of the suffering was craving for the bridge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you think that the bridge will get rid of all the suffering, but in fact...
[SPEAKER_01]: But you were suffering because you were basically trying to build that bridge, trying to gap, trying to surmount, trying to cross, which is impossible, trying to connect that which is, well, inconnectable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as you can see, simply through thinking that it is possible to build a bridge over that gap of your existence, you appropriate it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You appropriate the other shore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You appropriate the possibility of being on the other side.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where that bridge is built and the whole thing has been filled and connected and unified.
[SPEAKER_01]: But through seeing that this is impossible, you stop entertaining the notions of the other side of the gap, of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can see, through ownership, you maintain the notion of crossing, of building a bridge.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, through the efforts of building a bridge, through the assumption that it's possible to fill that gap,
[SPEAKER_01]: You keep assuming the ownership of the result of filling that gap, of that other side that you can close.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't necessarily try here and now, even in practicing restraint, the fact that you're maintaining the notion that it is possible to connect with that other side of that gap, means you are still very much within that assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're choosing not to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're choosing not to, yeah, you still own the other shore, through the possibility of, oh, I can cross there, through building this bridge over this insurmountable gap.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You fully understand that in Samantabhadra, that was... that is peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: The peace was not unifying broken pieces or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: The peace was abandoning them all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you have broken pieces of a vase, for as long as you hold on to deep perceptions of a vase, those pieces will be... well, will be valuable, will be useful, will be...
[SPEAKER_01]: Object of your effort to bring back the vows, to build it up as it was before, or whatever notions you might entertain, or emotional attachment towards it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you say, I don't care about it anymore, all those pieces become literally worthless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Entirely.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you... and especially when you recognize that you can't have the vows.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, well, you couldn't have had it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it was truly your vows all the time, you wouldn't have been broken in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have been in full control of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means it's independent of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, this gap that you're trying to surmount by pursuing your desires, it's independent of you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, it's insurmountable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, only through the notions of surmounting it, you are, yourself, fully responsible for maintaining the constant presence of the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop maintaining that, the desire fades, because it needs maintenance.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Nibbīla said, the object of desire is more desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the sole purpose of desire is the presence of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see that, because desire kind of tricks you by projecting a look.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what you're desiring for.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't see the nature of desire, because you're focused on a particular manifestation of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, a desire is already fulfilled.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire is fulfilled by itself, by being a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine by itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Only through the discrepancy, which you then assume, feels incomplete.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're fully responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know how people...
[SPEAKER_01]: The notion is, there's a desire, and then obviously there's a projected discrepancy of a fulfillment of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I do this, and this, and this, my desire will be fulfilled.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then you crave for that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you entertain, that's how you maintain the notion of desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you could equally, so to speak, fulfill your desire by forgetting about your desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you feel like, oh, if I pursue my desire, I fulfill my desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Equal to that pursuit, you could equally do that, just forget about your desire, and your desire will be equally fulfilled.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it was fulfilled to begin with.
[SPEAKER_01]: Desire in itself, it's a valid phenomenon, a reason as such, perfectly sufficient by itself, in itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the discrepancy created is in regard to another projected scenario, that it's incomplete in regard to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in itself, it's quite complete.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you were to forget about the scenario, the discrepancy is forgotten about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, desire is completely hurt.
[SPEAKER_00]: It ceases.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't be just forgetful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: What I mean by forgetting about desire is restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because by restraining, you stop pursuing it and then it falls off and you start thinking about something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if you can selectively forget only about desires, but don't forget about your forgetting, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you fulfill all your desires by restraints.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, you would.
[SPEAKER_01]: There will be true fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will bring all desires to an end, to a cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you cure your itch by not itching, by not scratching also.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because scratching makes making you worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that simple.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just most people are not strong enough to persist in non-scratching.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the reason they're not strong enough is because they don't practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't develop strength.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, they're fully responsible for being weak, for being unable to restrain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, they're fully responsible for being pulled by their desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I was...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was going to the beginning of that sutta, in nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we'll start off with Bhikkhu's essential pleasures are impermanent, hollow, false, deceptive.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are illusory.
[SPEAKER_00]: The prattle of fools.
[SPEAKER_00]: Essential pleasures here and now, and essential pleasures in life to come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Essential pleasures... perceptions here and now, and essential perceptions in life to come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Both alike are Māra's realm, Māra's domain, Māra's bait, Māra's hunting ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of them, these evil, unwholesome mental states such as covetousness, ill-will, and presumption arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they constitute an obstruction to a noble disciple in training here.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know what presumption is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't know what a part of the word is that he translates right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You get the context from the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when he, yeah, when a bhikkhu considers our sensual pleasures here and now, and so on, constitute an obstruction in the training, suppose I were to abide with the mind abundant and exalted, having transcended the world and made a firm determination with the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I do so, there will be no more evil, unwholesome mental states.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And with the abandoning of that, my mind will be unlimited, immeasurable and well-developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he practices in this way and frequently abides thus, his mind acquires confidence in the space... And there becomes the norm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the inter... inter... interval.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it requires development.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how, from abstraction, it's brought down to the actuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do it the first time, oh, this is abstract, but if you actually start pondering, discerning, establishing, understanding upon it, and then you abide in it frequently enough, it becomes a norm.
[SPEAKER_01]: It becomes a state that your mind is attained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, as he says, it is Mara's... Mara's fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's Mara's stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is... And what does it mean when saying this is Mara's?
[SPEAKER_01]: It means it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means it cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means it's owned by another.
[SPEAKER_01]: By Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what they said.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because people take that which belongs to Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mara does with them what he wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do they take?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or rather, what is it that belongs to Mara?
[SPEAKER_01]: It says, I belongs to Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: iPhones belong to Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hearer belongs to mārā, sounds belong to mārā.
[SPEAKER_01]: All the perceptions in its entirety belongs to mārā.
[SPEAKER_00]: But wouldn't it be somehow saying that there is a self and it's... there is a... No, there is a self, but it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's mārā's.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mārā is the ultimate self.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to stop regarding it as mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as this very thing says, stop regarding
[SPEAKER_01]: That it is possible to be yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're not taking it, it might be possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You should start thinking, no, it will not be possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is not possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be possible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever the Buddha talks about the future, then, in this sutta, he says, and it will not be for me in the future, sensual pleasures here and now, sensual pleasures to come.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's possibility of sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's equally impossible to be mine, as much as these present sensual pleasures are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And through abandoning that possibility, you actually abandon the present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because possibilities are subtler than there is in actual aspects.
[SPEAKER_01]: More general.
[SPEAKER_01]: Possibilities are more general.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're on the more general level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you know, the sense of self in regard to your five senses, in regard to experience as a whole, it's appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's regard dear and personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's welcomed.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's cherished.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's protected.
[SPEAKER_01]: You do the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: You let go of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You dismantle it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see that it's impossible to own it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that very sense of self that's right here, right now, in the center of your experience, no matter how vague it is, that sense of self, that's mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right here, in your core.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which wasn't your core.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was his core.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it was his all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why monks say, ah, Mahārāja, I see you.
[SPEAKER_01]: I see you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can see you.
[SPEAKER_01]: They see themselves thinking that, but they know, because that's not appropriate anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the Mahārāja.
[SPEAKER_01]: That self is the Mahārāja.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is his control.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is his domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why he controls all the beings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they're appropriate.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which is his.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which is him.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is Māra just another way of saying ignorance, religion?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, definitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of Egypt personified.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't... See, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're personified, but you don't... you can't get rid of that personification, because there will be appropriation of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to truly be able to get rid of the personality, so to speak, means, well, there would be a person.
[SPEAKER_01]: You would be in control of it, but you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all we can do is stop regarding it as yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is actually true.
[SPEAKER_01]: Get rid of... getting rid of...
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when that personality, if it's disowned, cannot be owned, fully understood, discerned, that you cannot possibly own it, that's when it just becomes manifested individuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these five aggregates arising in certain manners, based on certain habits, certain dried-up notions, or whatever else, but no more, no more abidjan, certainly no more person as in belonging to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: This does not belong to me, nor to anyone.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible for it to belong.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why Mara still comes to the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is Mara's domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the Buddha is not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Mara can't see him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or Mara can't see an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he's just not there anymore, ever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even as a possibility, Arahant is not there anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible for him to be there anymore, where Mahārāja can see him, where that personality can can take a grip of him again.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is well beyond it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's quite straightforward, in a way.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the mind is developed,
[SPEAKER_01]: To the proper discernment of every phenomenon, be it a thought, a feeling, a perception of this kind, of that kind, it's a reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start training like that, well, all of these things will kind of fit into place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, they have nothing to do with watching your nostrils and entering the mystical absorption states.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is all upon wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it is all upon it, with wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Come here, boy.
[SPEAKER_00]: I like it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I like the way the Buddha ended.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he says this, he says, meditate on under, do not delay, or else you will regret it later.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no reason to delay.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't own it right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that possibility of future ownership is present right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, delaying it means obstructing it unnecessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Really, don't delay.
[SPEAKER_01]: What for?
[SPEAKER_01]: The delay would come from that misperception, that, how do you want to say, in regards to sensuality, distortion.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where delay comes from.
[SPEAKER_01]: It wants to maintain itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mother wants to maintain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It needs control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, people think their thoughts are abstract, but it's actually the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's experience, present experience right here, that it's abstract in regard to thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts come first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because, as I said before, because your experience, well, experience of patujana is so centered around the sense of self, that is the center of the universe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Me and mine, I'm the reference point to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you're always bound with the senses, with the sensual, with the material aspects of things and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means that becomes your norm.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, even the most ordinary thoughts are regarded as, oh, this is just abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because every thought seems abstract,
[SPEAKER_01]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: abstracted from your current experience that you're used to, thoughts seem almost unreal.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why many people think thoughts are not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just in my head.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they got so bogged down in the sensual aspect of their experience, their minds are so down in that sort of domain, that sort of lowly sphere, that even the mere thinking feels abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's only because they're so used to this
[SPEAKER_01]: sphere of sensual, sphere of senses, and domain of senses, and control of senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: If somebody is to point out to you that that's the wrong way around, to turn the picture upside down, that which is first, you were putting second, well, somebody corrects that, then you reckon, no, thoughts are the real, thoughts are the center,
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of thoughts...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't mean just thinking any sort of nonsense in regard to your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the nature of thoughts is the is the center of experience and it's your experience that you're living.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the abstraction from that.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start... if you stop doing... if you stop maintaining that abstraction, if you acknowledge the nature of thoughts as present things that you could just... that you just designated, you will stop living that discrepancy that... which is abstraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, by basically, by freeing yourself from the notions of abstraction in regard to your own experience, you will be suffering less, because there will be less discrepancy created through such notions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for Pradyumna, thoughts are real.
[SPEAKER_01]: The rest of his experience is an abstraction, is a big mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a distortion, as the Buddha said, in terms of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And because they're so bound with that distortion, they think that's the real thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that which is... doesn't match it, they regard as, oh, this is abstracted from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I have the thought of nothingness, thought of impermeable, a thought, it's just a thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, if you dismiss it as just a thought, well, as I said before, you don't just shoot yourself in a foot, you shoot yourself in the head.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unless you seriously change those notions, because you'll never then recognize the nature of thoughts, which means you'll never then recognize the nature of your mind, because mind is thoughts, dhammas.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, dhamma, the capital D, is the knowledge of dhammas, like the small d. It's the phenomenology, the knowledge of phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you dismiss anything that appears in your mind as just an abstraction,
[SPEAKER_01]: You never look at it, which means you remain bogged down in sensuality, which is what you have at the time of dismissal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, you dismiss any helping hand, you're just gonna stay drowning.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you have notions of the nothingness, what we spoke about, that feels abstract in regard to where your mind is, because your mind hasn't been developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't dismiss it on that account.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just start developing it in regard to that which feels abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the more you develop it, the more you'll know about it, the less of that discrepancy will be maintained, which means the less of the abstraction you'll be living.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then you will understand, and you will be able to think nothingness right away, and have your mind set upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And as I said with the alternative,
[SPEAKER_01]: Option is, depending on person's faculties, he resolves upon it with wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: That means he doesn't necessarily need to develop it and make it actual to the full extent, because he has such a precise wisdom, that when people would think abstractly, he would think correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: What he would think, the person with the old wisdom,
[SPEAKER_01]: would stand for that which nothingness is, and he would know that, even without actually being there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he resolves upon that with his wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: He resolves, it is that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is what nothingness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he resolves upon it, and because that is what nothingness really is, he gets results of freedom that would come by being established upon that nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pañña vibhuti, liberated by wisdom.
[SPEAKER_01]: He resolves upon it with wisdom, stays really long enough, all the fetters fall off.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you have the other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You liberate the ego also, in both ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: You experience who touches it with the body, as the suttas will describe.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when that discrepancy between living body and the senses... Oh, full faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is fully developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, fully samādhi, fully extinguished.
[SPEAKER_01]: But abstract, it's only abstract if that discrepancy is created by what you're used to, that doesn't match that which you're thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you remember what?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is it, boy?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, we can't go for a walk now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh, shh
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll give it to the monkey.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if some of your thinking feels abstract, don't dismiss the thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just take it as, oh, there is a work to be done.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's abstract only because my present experience, present bodily experience doesn't match it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can't comprehend it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, comprehend it and you'll match it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the abstract thought of nothingness, is it fine?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still a valid direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a valid direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Based on what you read about nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, say, somebody, a completely different group, that doesn't follow any dhamma, starts talking about nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, then, even that abstract thought of that nothingness that this other different, different, different school teacher is talking about, won't necessarily be the right direction either, because it's so much off.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you read the suttas and when the Buddha talks about nothingness, having the faith from the Buddha and so on, then, well, you can be pretty certain.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not have experienced nothingness, have certainly not been established upon it, but you can be pretty certain that at least the direction where your abstract thought took you is probably the right one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's, you know, it's so vague in general, you really need to be seriously misled by instruction to go off that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, of course, there is a lot of work to go into that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, as I said, by reading the suttas, you can be rest assured that, well, at least the directions through your abstract thinking that you're getting, in terms of the instructions, are probably slightly right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is why it's important to have the right instruction, no matter how general it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if you were not to read the suttas, you'd read some other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stuff, whether presented as Buddhism or not, that can throw you off completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But in this case, the suttas... when you read... and that's why, if you keep reading about the suttas, even without any other input or explanation, if you... obviously, with this kind of view that, okay, abstract thinking is a direction that I need to develop, where it ceases to be abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, if you keep reading the suttas, that direction will crystallize more and more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you'll be thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be pondering it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be, as the Buddha said, you'll be investigating meaning.
[SPEAKER_01]: You wouldn't be leaving anything unturned.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you'll be working, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be walking.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the beginning, then you go east.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you just start going east, but, you know, you can go far off in many directions that are east.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you still keep going.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, the further you go, it will start narrowing down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you get more signs, more instructions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you recognize more of previous instructions that you heard, that you couldn't make much of at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, your direction will get more and more focused and pointed out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you're getting more precise.
[SPEAKER_01]: But none of that would be possible if you would have... if you would... if you... if you admit... sorry... if you dismissed the abstract thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is very arising because it's just thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's equally real.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's abstract only in regard to what you think it's more real.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're a putugena.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you should not be trusting what you think that it's more real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that is truly the real thing, you wouldn't be in a position.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You'll be an ananta.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't dismiss abstract thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to point it in the right direction through reading suttas and things that are least likely to be wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, keep drilling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, that's what I mean when I tell you, you have to be able to explain things to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't leave them vague, undefined.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it feels like this, or it feels like... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: What does it mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing the meaning means understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Knowing that there is nothing to be understood in these particular things, means you understood them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they are not worth of understanding, of pursuing further.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why, by reading the Suttas and Koan reading, you should be able to explain to yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so, it still feels abstract when I think about nothingness, but what it is?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is my... What is the meaning of it for me to that... at that point?
[SPEAKER_01]: What does it mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: How did I understand it?
[SPEAKER_01]: That doesn't mean you start going to some, like, psychotherapy, spiritual terminology, where you just start a while, it's like this, and it feels light, and it feels... No!
[SPEAKER_01]: What does it mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not asking you to describe how you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is your understanding at?
[SPEAKER_01]: And most importantly, is that understanding contributing to your freedom of suffering, and freedom from possibility to suffer, that is present?
[SPEAKER_01]: And if the understanding pertains to that, if understanding feels directly related or directly correlated to the freedom from suffering, then carry on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if it's irrelevant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I feel like this, or I feel like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that makes no difference.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, you suffer in regard to your feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I feel...
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel like Superman today.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel untouchable.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: What are you going to do when your feeling ceases?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just establish your peace upon your feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, the whole problem of not being free, not being peaceful, is depending upon feelings, being affected by them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's not be equitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's not equitable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't just give in to any kind of flamboyant description of what you might feel like when you think about nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, actually, develop it so you don't suffer on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, they wouldn't have laid it as a way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it doesn't pertain to freedom from suffering, means you're doing it wrong, or it's a wrong instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it since came from the Buddha, it's not the wrong instruction, thus you're doing it wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always a good criteria of, okay, I've been pursuing this line of thinking in regard to base of nothingness.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been dwelling on the notions of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I know... can I suffer less on account of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Then you... like, even with your intelligence, you could see.
[SPEAKER_01]: This seems that if I were to develop it, I would be untouchable by this unpleasant feeling when it arises.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that would also... because feeling is inseparable from perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if I'm entirely surmounting the perception, and free from it, and established in that base that's higher than that perception, none of the feelings that arise on account of that perception I can perceive can affect me, because they pertain to perception, not to me, because I'm out of that perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, it is freeing you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even less extra.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's abstract for somebody who's just... whose mind is far removed from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, as a thought, as a value direction, it must not be dismissed at any cost.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't necessarily follow it to such an extent, you can just go back to the obvious one.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the perceptions of the forest, you abandon perceptions of the village, perceptions of the crowded life, perceptions of the people, perceptions of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, pursue the perceptions which have a flavor.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of freedom, the taste of freedom, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, that's... Yeah, these perceptions, I have not clearly developed them, but it seems to me, based on my limited discernment at this point, they're more likely to result in freedom than perceptions of hanging around the village.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, I should follow them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, by following them, you come closer to other perceptions that were there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you actually... oh, yeah, no, I was right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you define your taste of freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: You gain confidence in the taste of freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you know, ah, it is free.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if abstract thinking of freedom would stand for that which freedom actually is, freedom from craving, freedom from suffering, all you have to do is keep repeating it, and you will be resolved upon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're walking in that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, you'll be resolved upon it, which means everything will be dragged into that direction, that third experience, because you anchored it there, and give it some time, and all the factors will fall off.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, yeah, this was right, even as an abstract thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was very accurate.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, obviously, I was dismissing it, because I was so centered at the opposite end.
[SPEAKER_01]: But fortunately, out of faith,
[SPEAKER_01]: And persistence.
[SPEAKER_01]: I kept doing it, and I had it rooted, I had it anchored there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And look!
[SPEAKER_01]: All this experience that was bogged down in sensuality, the mind that was fully controlled and just disturbed and abused by sensuality and everything else, has been dragged out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And look, now it's there, where that imperturbable is, and all that swamp is abandoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's abstract now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Shifts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you're thinking about sensuality that you have fully understood as pretty much inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's possible to... it's impossible to own.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's abstract thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are abstracted from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can see how much harm can be caused by the casual Buddhist advice that you often read and hear.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or just stop thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ignoring all the contradictions that a sentence would imply.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thoughts are a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: I stop thinking and I'm at peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you'll never try to think properly and you certainly will never be able to, well, to think.
[SPEAKER_01]: To develop your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And again, when I say think, I don't mean to sit and theorize or rationalize what makes sense to you in your putrugena-centered experience around your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that the thinking is slave to the senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or it should be, at least.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, developing the thinking is based on the suttas, however abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't dismiss it, but actually pursue their direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it will cease to be abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: One thing for sure, none of these states, space of nothingness, space of neither perception or perception, one intent upon nibbāna, will be arising by a chance, given to you by some meditative technique that kind of just made these things happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You develop them through discerning what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, if your thought of what they are is accurate thought, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are rooted in that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you have to keep doing it long enough until all the fetters fade.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right view is the knowledge of nibbāna, knowledge of freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now you can pursue it, or you can choose to be distracted in regard to it, but you can't forget about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, at most, in several lifetimes, you'll do away with all the fetters, but maybe even before.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's what it talks about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sotāpanna is being reborn.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not all of them need to sit through several lifetimes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some of them become arhants before they land into another river.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like a loose translation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or upon landing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or in the space in between, all those pali terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, you could have taken to different faculties and then, even in that state in between, you carry on.
[SPEAKER_01]: You carry on the development of that idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, at most, several lifetimes, but not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's depending on how much effort... How much effort you put in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: How accurate your thoughts of what nibbāna is actually are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no... and that's one thing you realize.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you think nibbāna is, can be right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't have a reference point to it externally, whereby you see, okay, this is what nibbāna is, and now I can correct my thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can only see it from the inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you will know that this is the right thinking when you're fully free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you know, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why sometimes anāgāmī overestimated himself.
[SPEAKER_01]: They thought they were fully nibbāna, but they were not quite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the things get a bit subtler later on, in terms of conceit and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, some people might not necessarily see if the circumstances are not prompting them to see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the point is, you can't have an external view of anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means then, your abstract thinking, or non-abstract thinking, is all you have to stand for that thing which you're aiming at for freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I meant in the essay, Not Perceiving the Feeling and Determining Determinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: That because of which you have thoughts of that, because of which you have thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you can only think in regard to that which you're thinking, but that's already another thought that you're thinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you can't step outside of your thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let alone that you should dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you have to do then, is make sure you stop assuming that thought to be that which it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that thought will stand for that which that thought is.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other way, have an accurate thought of what nibbāna is, have an accurate thought of what a way out of suffering is, have an accurate thought of what craving is, have an accurate thought of what matter is, have an accurate thought of what feeling is, have an accurate thought of what perception is, have an accurate thought of what intentions are, have an accurate thought of what consciousness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because through an inaccurate thought, you introduce assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The discrepancy of inaccuracy is the extent of your assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Extend to your rūpa then.